Preliminary Guide to the Egbert S. Oliver Papers, 1935-1983
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Egbert S. Oliver papers 1935-1983
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Oliver, Egbert S. (Egbert Samuel), 1902-
4.5 Linear feet
Professor of American Literature at Willamette University and Portland State University; served as a Fulbright lecturer to India.
Collection includes an unpublished manuscript, Melville, Rebellious Optimist; a holograph manuscript of Elizabeth Shaw and Herman Melville: The Story of Their Family Life; correspondence with publishers, microfilm of recommendations to the Dept. of State for Herman and Gansevoort Melville’s consular and other appointments, letters from colleagues, newsletters of the Melville Society, a sketch of Vernon Parrington, clippings and other miscellaneous items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Egbert S. Oliver Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1980.
Collection Overview
Collection includes an unpublished manuscript, Melville, Rebellious Optimist; a holograph manuscript of Elizabeth Shaw and Herman Melville: The Story of Their Family Life; correspondence with publishers; a microfilm of recommendations to the Dept. of State for Herman and Gansevoort Melville’s consular and other appointments; letters from colleagues; newsletters of the Melville Society; a sketch of Vernon Parrington; and clippings and other miscellaneous items. Portions of this collection may be unprocessed and may require further processing before research use. Acquired as part of the Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Authors, American -- 20th century
Oliver, Egbert S. (Egbert Samuel), 1902-
Melville, Herman, 1819-1891 -- Periodicals
Parrington, Vernon Louis, 1871-1929
Melville, Herman, 1819-1891 -- Family
Melville, Elizabeth Shaw, 1822-1906
Melville, Herman, 1819-1891 -- Criticism and interpretation
Melville Society -- Periodicals
Novelists, American -- 19th century -- Biography
Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography
Contents of Collection
- General Papers Series, 1935-1983, (3 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1981 (Box 1)
  - Writings, 1935-1983 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1980 (Box 4)
- India Series, (4 boxes)
  - Alphabetical File (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Family letters, 1955-1971 (Box 5)
  - Universities and Conferences (Box 6)
  - Miscellany File (Box 7)
- Melville Papers Series, (2 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1955 (Box 8)
  - Miscellany
  - Manuscripts
  - Unpublished manuscript, Herman Melville: Rebellious Optimist (Box 9)